Hello everyone.
Welcome to our sixth
lecture on respiratory
physiology. Today,
we're going to explore
ventilation-perfusion
relationships. This
is Dr. Jörg LeHest.
The session objectives
are in line with the event
description. This event
focuses on the challenges
of respiratory gas exchange
due to gravity effects
on the lungs. The session
emphasizes compensatory
bronchoconstriction and
compensatory hypoxic
vasoconstriction as the two
main mechanisms ensuring
physiological veq conditions
across the lungs the
session further highlights
the challenges of
physiologic and non-physiologic
shunts on gas exchange
this is a reminder that
pulmonary circulation
and systemic circulation
are very different
So while pulmonary
circulation operates on low
pressure, systemic
circulation operates on high
pressure. Both, however,
handle the same blood
volume, which is approximately
six liters per minute,
which is approximately
one and a half gallons.
How is this possible?
Well, it's possible
because pulmonary
blood vessels have
a larger compliance.
So as we explored in
previous lectures,
that means that pulmonary
blood vessels are easier
to expand and absorb
larger amounts of blood.
For that purpose,
their walls are thinner
and they're also
less muscularized.
As a result, there's
less pressure and less
resistance, despite the
fact that it handles
the same volume as
systemic circulation.
Another thing that's
unique to pulmonary
circulation is that there are
bronchial and thepsian
contributions.
So we already talked about
bronchial circulation,
that about two-thirds
of the oxygen-poor
blood from the bronchial
circulation just merges
into the pulmonary
circulation via shunts.
So that's actually a
mixing of oxygen-poor blood
which is coming in
through the bronchial
circulation with oxygen
-rich blood which just comes
from the lung through the
pulmonary circulation.
The same is true for
the blood vessels that
feed the heart muscle.
Those are the ones
called the thepsian
veins and these also
merge right into the
pulmonary circulation.
This is an example of such
a shunt which in reality
exists in the form of
bronchial and Debsian veins.
So instead of going
the regular route and
engaging in gas exchange
with the alveoli, about
2% of our cardiac
output goes into shunts.
Because there is no gas
exchange, the partial pressure
of oxygen and also carbon
dioxide is the same in
the shunted blood as it is
in mixed venous circulation.
Then the shunted blood is
just added to the blood
that returns from a gas
exchange and then back into
the left heart and into
the systemic blood supply.
let's now look at
some non-physiologic
examples let's begin
with right to left shunts
it's most important to
remember that right to
left shunts always
cause hypoxemia and that
they cannot be corrected
with breathing oxygen
and we'll see in a second
why that is the case
so here we have a shunt
situation that exists because
the ventricular septum
has not fully formed and
oxygen poor blood that has
just returned to the right
side of the heart is mixed
in with oxygen rich blood
which has just returned from
the lungs so this explains
why this cannot be fixed
with breathing o2 because
while the um blood oxygen
concentration under certain
circumstances might be
um increased a little bit
by breathing o2 this effect
is completely undone with
mixing oxygen-poor blood
with it before it then
returns into systemic
circulation here into the aorta.
One of the syndromes
that are caused by
a shunt like this,
which you would
definitely cover with
our clinical faculty,
is called Eisenmenger syndrome,
but be aware that there are
others. What's important
to consider with a shunt is
what the size of the shunt
is so and that can be
estimated with a shunt fraction
equation so from the previous
slide you already know
that the size of our
physiologic shunts is about two
percent of blood volume and
anything above that would
be non-physiologic and what
you would do to calculate
size is now determine the
amount of shunted blood and
build a quotient with cardiac
output and that will give
you the shunt fraction so
the size of the shunt here
we have two examples of
left to right shunts which
are distinctly different
compared to the right
to left shunt that we
looked at in the slide
before most importantly in
a way that these typically
typically do not cause
hypoxemia these are two
of the more common examples
in each of them make
up about 20 15 to 20
percent of all congenital
heart defects each so
together 30 to 40 percent
Here on the left, we
have depicted an atrial
septal defect, and what
happens is that as blood
returns freshly oxygenated
from the lungs, some
portion of it through
this atrial septal defect
mixes back in with the
oxygenated blood. However,
whatever else, the other
portion of the blood that
just returned will normally
descend into the left
ventricle and then be ejected
into systemic circulation.
So in other words,
the systemic circulation
will receive fully oxygenated
blood, and therefore, it is
unlikely that this causes
hypoxemia. But whether it
does or not also depends
on the size of this defect.
So if the defect is small,
hypoxemia will most
likely not ensue.
And however, if the
effect is very large, then
the efficiency of the
left side of the heart
might be affected, which
could cause hypoxemia.
Now, this is typically
a congenital heart
defect, and it needs to be
fixed right away, because
if it is not, then
the heart must work
harder to stay as efficient
as it would if there
was no defect, and that
will, over time, wear
the heart out and cause
cardiac hypertrophy.
As, by the way, in the
example that we saw in the
slide before, that also
causes cardiac hypertrophy,
anything that requires
the heart to work harder.
Here on the left
-hand side, we have
another left to
right shunt, and this
one is called patent
ductus arteriosus.
And what happens is that
this is a congenital defect
in the pulmonary artery.
And so there's a gap
between the pulmonary
artery and the aorta.
So this defect,
this ductus arteriosus,
connects pulmonary
artery blood with
aortic blood. And then
aortic blood, which
is rich in oxygen
because it just
returned from the lungs,
mixes in to oxygen poor blood
in the pulmonary artery.
But because the blood
reaching the systemic
circulation is fully
oxygenated, also this
defect is not likely
to cause hypoxemia. But
again, it depends on
the size of this defect.
One question might
ensue, why is oxygen
-poor blood from the
pulmonary artery
not mixing in with oxygen
-rich blood in the aorta?
Because that would clearly
cause hypoxemia, correct?
Can you figure it out?
I'll give you a second.
Well, that's because
the blood in the
pulmonary artery is in a
low pressure situation,
like the entire
pulmonary circulation.
In the aorta, however,
we have a high pressure
situation because the
aortic blood is part of the
systemic circulation. So
because of the pressure being
much higher in the aorta,
blood will always flow
from the aorta into the
pulmonary artery through the
ductus arteriosus and
never in the opposite way.
Hypoxic vasoconstrictions
is one of
the major ways through
which regulation
of pulmonary blood
flow can occur.
This mechanism exists to
prevent the unnecessary
perfusion of poorly
ventilated alveoli.
It thereby operates
in the opposite
way as most other
capillary systems.
So most other capillary
systems, the blood
vessels that bring in
blood, they expand upon
poor oxygenation, just
to remedy the situation.
Now in the lungs, this
is exactly the opposite,
and it's in an effort to
increase efficiency of
blood oxygenation and
the removal of carbon
dioxide where the blood
then is being shunned being
pushed into areas that
are better ventilated
um normally in the
normal circumstances
oxygen from the blood
vessels that have just
received oxygen from
the alveoli passes
by vascular i'm sorry
passes by vascular
smooth muscle cells,
and nothing happens.
If the alveoli are less
ventilated, then there is
less oxygen translating into
those capillaries, and the
surrounding smooth muscle
cells sense this shortage
in oxygen and react to this
with vasoconstrictions.
So while the mechanism
is not 100 percent
understood yet, it's
hypothesized that the
depolarization that
is necessary for this
vasoconstriction is based
on the activity of calcium
channels in response
to low oxygen levels.
The process of hypoxic
vasoconstriction
is actually pretty
straightforward.
You can see on the left
that in the system where
everything is well matched,
things flow and are
unrestricted whereas on the
right if in one of those
alveoli the partial pressure
of oxygen falls below 70
millimeter mercury then the
capillaries feeding into
it are being restricted in
flow and that is of course
to reroute the blood into
areas that are better
better ventilated.
One of the antidotes
that's good to keep
in mind is nitric
oxide. So nitric oxide
is a general relaxant
for smooth muscle
cells. And also in the
respiratory system,
the smooth muscle
that is wrapped around
these blood vessels
responds to nitric
oxide by opening up
the blood vessels.
In this manner,
hypoxic vasoconstriction
can be used for ventilation
perfusion matching as seen
here in this example with
focal hypoxia. So here we
have an area that is poorly
ventilated in this lung
and the resistance arteries
that have a lot of smooth
muscle around them can actually
squeeze shut and then shift
the blood flow to areas
that are better ventilated
which are the pink areas.
Now in contrast to focal
hypoxia there can also be
global hypoxia and that's of
course very bad because as
a result of global hypoxia
it gets very hard for any
part of the lung to partake
in gas exchange. So that's
a situation that we already
explored as a resulting
from high altitude because
at high altitude we can
depending on how high exactly
the concentration of oxygen
in the ambient air can be very
low and can be significantly
lower than 70 millimeters
mercury which would
cause global hypoxia of the
entire lung this situation
also exists in fetuses
because they don't need their
lungs yet so there it's
physiological however if it is
pathologic then it may
significantly alter vascular
resistance and against this
vascular resistance the heart
has to work again because
we depend on oxygen. And
if this persists, if this
condition persists for too
long, the affected person
can end up with cardiac
hypertrophy and oftentimes
with right-sided heart failure.
One set of pulmonary
vascular behavior that can
be regulated in order to
overcome a ventilation
to perfusion mismatch
is the behavior that
we have already looked
at of alveolar vessels,
which basically line an
alveolus and are very
close to the alveolar
surface, compared
to extra alveolar vessels,
which are a little
bit removed from the
alveolar compartment.
I hope you remember
that extra alveolar
vessels had the most
resistance at low lung
volumes, and then the
resistance, I'm talking
about the pulmonary
vascular resistance,
gets diminished as the
lung volume increases.
The opposite is true for
alveolar vessels, which
are capillaries, those
are pulmonary capillaries,
their pulmonary
vascular resistance is
the lowest at small
lung volumes and then
increases as the
lung volume expands.
So those are the two
dotted lines. The
combination of both effects
you can see here as the
solid line, which
depicts the combination
of of pulmonary vascular
resistance based on
alveolar vessels and
extra alveolar vessels.
So one can see that at
the functional residual
capacity volume, the
overall pulmonary vascular
resistance of the entire
system is the lowest, and with
volume smaller than
that, it's increased and
with volumes higher than
that, it's also increased.
This is the list of
select vasoconstrictors
and dilators that I've
shown to you before.
There's also an airway
constrictor here. So
with the point being
that those are chemicals
that can be used for,
or I should say against
mismatches of ventilation
to perfusion when things
such as hypoxic
vasoconstriction have occurred
and or adjustments to
pulmonary vascular resistance
of alveolar and extra
alveolar blood vessels.
Here we're looking
at the ventilation
to perfusion
distribution in the lung.
Whenever you see a dot
on top of any of those
letters in physiology, it
indicates a rate rather
than a static number, so
change over time, but it
doesn't affect any of
our other considerations.
I hope you remember that
the lungs are divided
into three zones, one,
two, three, they're
called zones of west,
with one occurring at
the apex of the lungs
and three at the base.
Now when we consider the
gravitational effects on
blood flow, then it's easy
to imagine that gravity
pulls blood down the axis
of the lungs towards the
bottom. So for For that
reason, the blood flow is
the lowest on the top and
the highest on the bottom.
Now alveolar ventilation
follows the same
trend, however,
because air being less
affected by gravity
than blood, the effect
is less pronounced,
but also we see lower
ventilation at the
top and higher
ventilation at the bottom.
because of the disproportional
reaction of blood
versus air in response to
gravity the ventilation
to perfusion ratio is
actually the highest
on top so here in the
middle it would be point
eight that's ideal but
it's around three in zone
one and that's because
yes there is poor
ventilation but But the
blood flow is even poorer.
So ventilation is
affected, but not as much
as perfusion. And
therefore the ventilation
to perfusion ratio is
the highest on top.
Now being high as a
ventilation, having a high
ventilation to perfusion
ratio is not a great thing.
So as I said, the ideal is
around 0.8. so that's when
things are going the smoothest
so 3 is not great and
also at the bottom I mean
the bottom with 0.6 is
close to 0.8 but there's still
a ventilation to perfusion
mismatch and the causing
causative agent is gravitation
now when we're looking
at the partial pressure
of oxygen in the pulmonary
artery and do the same for
the partial pressure of
carbon dioxide we find that
there's also a ventilation
to perfusion mismatch result
on top as it is on bottom
because ideally we would
see 100 millimeters mercury
here for oxygen and 40
millimeters mercury for
carbon dioxide this is just a
different depiction of what
we just looked at So here
we have the partial pressure
of carbon dioxide in
mmHg plotted against the
partial pressure of oxygen in
mmHg. Let's start here
with inspired air. We know
that the partial pressure of
inspired air or ambient air
is about 160 mmHg of inspired
air due to the addition
of water vapor it's only
150 millimeters mercury.
As we hit zone one at
the apex of the lungs,
we saw that the ventilation to
perfusion ratio
was the highest,
so both ventilation
and perfusion were
reduced at zone one,
but the perfusion was
reduced more severely
than ventilation,
therefore having a VQ
of about 3 in Zone 1.
In Zone 2, they're
perfectly matched,
and a ventilation
-to-perfusion ratio
of 0.8 indicates
that perfect match.
So Zone 3,
again, we had a ventilation
-to-perfusion mismatch with
a number of 0.63. Again, 0
.8 would be ideal and that
is largely to the effect
of gravity on the on the
blood which tends to pool
at the base of the lungs so
here we have two extreme
situations in terms of
ventilation and perfusion and
then in the middle we have
normal again the two mechanisms
that can allow compensation
are brontoconstriction
and compensatory hypoxic
vasoconstriction. We looked
at both of them already.
So the first example, so
let's start here. Normal
is in the middle. So we
have perfect matching of
blood flow or perfusion
and ventilation, and a
ventilation-perfusion ratio
of around 0.8 is perfect.
So that's the best it
gets. That's where we
get 100% of the gases
of oxygen and carbon
dioxide that we need
to get across the
diffusion barrier across
in a timely manner.
now in this example here on
the left we have a situation
of shunt perfusion so you
know that a shunt means
that as blood flows through
the area its gas concentration
doesn't change so it
doesn't pick up oxygen and
it does not release carbon
dioxide and that's because
this alveolus here allows
for no ventilation.
So we have wasted perfusion
due to the lack of
ventilation and because there
is no gas change associated
with this, we should call
this shunt perfusion.
And the VQ is low,
so low ventilation
and normal perfusion
makes for an overall
low ventilation to
perfusion ratio.
So I said here in the middle,
it's optimal, it's 0.8.
In the example here
on the right, we're
looking at dead
space ventilation.
So that means we
have a very high
ventilation rate, but
there's no perfusion.
So that's wasted ventilation,
and this can happen
as a result of a pulmonary
embolism. So that basically
clogs this pulmonary
capillary. So no gas exchange
can happen. But because
ventilation is happening,
the ventilation to
perfusion rate is
high.
Here are some situations
that are consistent with what
we already talked about.
Here we have the situation
of dead space and dead
space means that we have
perfect ventilation but we
have zero perfusion that means
for the gases the gases
that come in here into this
alveolus and that leave
the alveolus have the same
concentration of oxygen and
carbon dioxide so that's
the dead space situation if
you calculate the ventilation
over perfusion ratio
because ventilation is huge
and perfusion doesn't
exist um then you end up
with infinity and infinity
valium so ventilation
is infinitesimally larger
than perfusion um in
the next panel here we
have a high ventilation
to perfusion ratio that
is a situation that we see
at the apex or top of the
lung so we have normal
ventilation we have little
perfusion so that means that
the oxygen that's in here
in this alveus has a lot
of time to get across into
this reduced blood flow so
the partial pressure of
oxygen inside the arterial
blood that this capillary
gets gives rise to is high
and And also, the same
accounts for carbon dioxide.
The carbon dioxide that
comes in here for exchange
has a lot of time to engage
in gas exchange because,
again, the amount of
air is so large and
the blood flow is very,
very little. So that
means that the partial
pressure of carbon
dioxide as a result
is comparatively low.
um in the next panel we
have the situation in zone
three at the bottom of the
lung so we have a ventilation
to perfusion ratio where
the ventilation is is
good but the perfusion is too
large so they're mismatched
so that's at the bottom
of the lung situation um
so that means that there
is more blood flow than we
have gas available for
exchange that reduces the
partial pressure of oxygen
as the blood moves through
the capillary and then into
the arterial and the same
is for carbon dioxide so
there's a lot of carbon
dioxide that comes this way
but you know the ventilation
is not matched and not
all of the carbon dioxide
that comes in can be
efficiently exchanged so that's
why it remains high as it
moves through the system
lastly we have a left to
right shunt so ventilation to
perfusion ratio is zero
because um anything divided
by zero is zero that's
mathematically the case um and
the gas concentrations going
in and out of the shunt
are the same and that's
true for oxygen and also
carbon dioxide so out of
these considerations there are
two main points um that
that result and those are
that in any sort of
ventilation to perfusion defect
we always see hypoxemia
and so whatever it is that
affects the gas exchange a
gas exchange ratio, if you
want to look at it this
way, will lead to hypoxemia,
which is defined as
decreased partial pressure of
oxygen in the respiratory
arteriola system, and it will
also lead to hypercapnia.
So, if exchange doesn't
function properly, then we end
up with more carbon dioxide
in these pulmonary arterioles
then there should be
because efficient exchange
or exchange has not occurred
efficiently efficiently so
it's good to have various
perspectives and so for a
third time we're going to
look at ventilation to
perfusion defects one more one
last time so on the left
we have a normal situation
with a matched ventilation
to perfusion ratio ideally
that's 0.8 in this situation
in alveoli we have a
partial pressure of oxygen
of about 100 millimeters
mercury it's not 160 as in
ambient air a because water
vapor has been added that reduces
it by about 10 millimeters
mercury and also there
sits in this space mixed
air which comes from previous
expirations so the most
that we can ever get here
in the alveolar space under
those conditions is 100
millimeter mercury as the
blood flows through the
arterial oxygen concentration
will equilibrate with this
so it's also 100 because of
the the mixed quality of
air inside this alveolus
which comes from previous
inspirations and expirations
the alveolar carbon dioxide
concentration is around 40
the blood comes in with 45
so it equilibrates it will
equilibrate with the 40
and then once the blood has
passed through. They both
will be at 40. So the common
theme here is that blood,
as blood passes through,
at an optimal ventilation
to perfusion ratio,
the concentrations of
arterial blood in oxygen
and carbon dioxide will
be identical to those
in alveolar air, and
that's the case here.
in this case we have a
pulmonary embolus so an
obstruction of a pulmonary
blood vessel so that is
synonymous with that
space ventilation so we're
ventilating a space that has
no perfusion in this case
because we have ventilation
that has some value and
perfusion that is zero
if you divide some value
by zero, then the result
is infinity, so that's why
the ventilation and
perfusion ratio is infinity.
The alveolar oxygen's
concentration is higher than
100 because over time, if
this happens over time here,
there's the fusion happening,
so there's no breathing
in or breathing out that
could change the alveolar
gas concentration in
regards to oxygen and carbon
dioxide so this will over
time equilibrate with the
ambient air so that's why
the alveolar partial pressure
of oxygen is the same
as that of ambient air
minus the moisture which is
always here so that's why
it's 150 and not 160 and the
partial pressure of carbon
dioxide in this alveolus
is zero which is the
same as in ambient air then
the third situation is that
the airway is obstructed
so that is equivalent with
a shunt perfusion so we
have no airflow going on.
The blood that's entering
with values of carbon
dioxide and oxygen does
no gas exchange because
that's impossible due to
the obstruction and it
should leave the same way
with the same concentration
as it came in. That's
the nature of a shunt
and lo and behold the
arterial concentration of
oxygen is that of mixed
venous blood, which is 40.
And the arterial concentration
of carbon dioxide
is also that of mixed
venous blood, which is 46.
And here another board
-style question for you.
A 32-year-old female is
admitted to the intensive
care unit with acute
respiratory distress
syndrome secondary to
severe atypical pneumonia.
Her chest x-ray shows
diffused bilateral alveolar
infiltrates and extensive
fluid-filled collapsed
alveoli known as atelectasis
that's creating a massive
physiological right to
left shunt the resident on
duty places the patient
a 100 supplemental oxygen
via non-rebreather mask
but her arterial oxygen
saturation remains critically
low at 82 percent which
of the following best
explains why her hypoxemia
is highly resistant to
supplemental oxygen therapy
A suggests that the
high concentration of
oxygen causes widespread
pulmonary vasodilation,
which increases
the shunt fraction.
So high concentration
of oxygen doesn't do
anything to the shunt
fraction because the
shunt fraction is the
fraction that just passes
through the lung
without having access to
alveolar um oxygen because
of the collapse as in
this situation so um that's
why a is incorrect um
it's noteworthy though
that unlike other tissues
in the body the lungs do
react with vasodilation
to um higher oxygen
levels um and that is in
an effort to make sure
that areas that are well
ventilated also receive
um an adequate amount
of blood supply to
pick up oxygen and get
rid of co2 effectively
um but you know because
of the collapse um
that's not the issue here
b supplemental oxygen decreases
the affinity of hemoglobin
for any remaining oxygen
in the systemic circulation
it's actually the opposite
so higher oxygen levels
lead to a conformational
change of hemoglobin from the
taut confirmation to the
relaxed and in its relaxed
form it can take up oxygen
more easily the oxygen gas is
highly insoluble in blood
plasma preventing any increase
in dissolved oxygen content
it's only a small amount
of oxygen that's carried
in plasma because it is
rather insoluble as compared
to co2 so but because of that
circumstance that we're
talking about very little that
couldn't explain the low
oxygen arterial oxygen
saturation in this patient
he the elevated oxygen levels
inhibit the enzyme carbonic
anhydrase blocking normal gas
transit well we're talking
about the bicarbonate buffer
system here which is where
the this enzyme is active
and the enzyme just does
not respond to oxygen levels
so that leaves us with C
and C suggests the inspired
oxygen cannot reach the
blood flowing through the
collapsed unventilated alveoli
and that is actually the
definition of a shunt so
that's the correct answer as
always please look at constanzo
at the summary portion of
the respiratory physiology
chapter use the self quiz
question and the answers
at the end of the book and
there's also scholar x all
of that you can find in the
updated cpg lastly please give
me a shout out let me know
how this has been for you um
and let me know what works
and give me some pointers
as what you would like to
change if you have any thank
you and have a great day